Guide to the Steven Chu Papers SC0828
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Steven Chu papers
1949-2013
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Chu, Steven.
SC0828
32 Linear Feet
Papers pertain primarily to topics in physics and include notes, overhead transparencies from his lectures, reprints, articles, memos, proposals, correspondence, charts, and drawings. Subjects include electric dipole moment, diode lasers, and dye lasers; and there are some materials pertaining to departmental matters. Also included in the collection is the 1989 paper by P. Galison, B. Hevly, and R. Lowen, "Controlling the Monster - Stanford and the Growth of Physics Research, 1935-1962."
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Steven Chu is the William R. Kenan, Jr. Professor of Physics and Professor of Molecular and Cellular Physiology at Stanford University. From January 2009 until April, 2013, Dr. Chu served as the 12th U.S. Secretary of Energy under President Barack Obama. During his tenure, the Department of Energy annual budget was approximately $26 Billion and was entrusted an additional $36 B through the Recovery Act.
As the longest serving Energy Secretary, he began several initiatives including ARPA-E (Advanced Research Projects Agency – Energy), the Energy Innovation Hubs, and the Clean Energy Ministerial meetings. During his time at the DOE, the deployment of renewable energy in the U.S. doubled. As the first scientist to head the DOE, Dr. Chu helped identify and recruit a dozen outstanding scientists and engineers; he worked to create a “Bell Labs” culture in ARPA-E, which is now being disseminated in other parts of the Energy Department such as the solar photovoltaic program, “SunShot.”
From 2004-2009, he was the Director of the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory and Professor of Physics and Professor of Molecular and Cell Biology at the University of California Berkeley. Prior to those positions, he was the Theodore and Francis Geballe Professor of Physics and Applied Physics at Stanford University. During this time at Stanford (1987 – 2004) he twice chaired the Department of Physics and helped start Bio-X, a multi-disciplinary initiative that brings together the physical and biological sciences with engineering and medicine. From 1978 – 1987, he worked at AT&T Bell Laboratories, including four years as Head of the Quantum Electronics Research Department.
Chu’s thesis and postdoctoral work was one of the first successful observations of parity non-conservation in atomic transitions, confirming the Weinberg-Salam-Glashow theory that unified weak and electromagnetic interactions. While at Bell Laboratories Chu and A. Mills performed the first laser spectroscopy of positronium, the fundamental atom consisting of an electron and the positron, and muonium, an atom consisting of a proton and muon. While also at Bell Labs, Chu also made contributions in condensed matter studies of exciton energy transfer, Anderson Localization, and made the first observation of anomalous (faster than light and negative velocity) pulse propagation.
While at Bell labs, Chu led the group that showed how to first cool and then trap atoms with light. The “optical tweezers” trap, first demonstrated during the course of the atom trapping work, is widely used in biology. Other contributions include the demonstration of the magneto-optic trap, the most widely used atom trap today. At Stanford, he developed the theory of laser cooling of actual, multilevel atoms (also independently by Claude Cohen-Tannoudji and Jean Dalibard), and demonstrated the first atomic fountain/fountain atomic clock. For this work, he was the co-recipient the Nobel Prize in Physics in 1997. He group also introduced atom interferometry based on optical pulses of light, a technique that has remained the most precise form of atom interferometry after two decades. Chu and his colleagues used atom interferometry test the equivalence principle between a macroscopic object and a quantum object to an accuracy of several parts per billion and in the precision measurement of the coupling constant that defines the strength of electromagnetic interactions.
Using the optical tweezers, Chu introduced methods to simultaneously visualize and manipulate single bio-molecules. This work led to investigations in polymer dynamics (using DNA as the model polymer) that included studies of reputation and relaxation in polymer solutions, the discovery of “molecular individualism”, and the observation of hysteresis in the coil-stretch transition.
In single molecule biology, Chu, with James Spudich and Robert Simmons, designed and developed an apparatus that was able to measure the force on an actin filament held by optical tweezers when myosin molecular motors attached to the actin hydrolyzed ATP. Chu and his group were the first group to use FRET (Fluorescence Resonance Energy Transfer) to study the individual molecules tethered to a glass surface.
This advance allowed the Chu and his collaborators to perform the first single molecule studies of the unfolding and multiple pathways of the refolding of the Tetrahymena, the accommodation and proofreading mechanism of the ribosome, and studies of the enzymology of the hairpin ribozyme and helicase enzymes. During this time Chu helped start Bio-X at Stanford University, a multi-disciplinary program that combined the physical and biological sciences with medicine and engineering.
More recent single molecule studies the role of SNARE and associated proteins responsible for neural vesicle fusion and the demonstration of the assembly of the pre-initiation complex and followed by eukaryotic transcription. His group has also been applying sub-wavelength optical imaging to studies of cancer signaling, the structural development of growing bio-films, while improving the spatial resolution to sub-nanometer resolution by developing a method to measure and correct the non-uniform response of light in CCD cameras.
During the past ten years, Chu has also become active in marshaling scientists and resources to address the energy problem with new pathways to sustainable, CO2 neutral energy. He co-chaired the Inter-Academy Council report “Transitioning to Sustainable Energy.” He was a member of the NAS/NAE/NRC committees that produced the reports, “Rising Above the Gathering Storm” and “America’s Energy Future.” The “Rising Above the Gathering Storm” report recommended the establishment of a new funding agency within the Department of Energy, ARPA-E (Advanced Research Projects Agency – Energy) that would focus on high-risk high reward energy research that could result in the invention of disruptive technologies.
Chu led the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (LBNL) from August 2004 to January 2009. He stepped down to become the 12th U.S. Secretary of Energy until April 2013. As the fist scientist to hold a cabinet position and the longest serving Energy Secretary, he began several initiatives including ARPA-E (Advanced Research Projects Agency – Energy), the Energy Innovation Hubs, and the Clean Energy Ministerial meetings. Also during his tenure, the deployment of renewable energy doubled in the U.S. and solar energy deployment increased 10-fold. Chu was personally involved in recruiting numerous outstanding scientists and engineers into the DOE, creating a more Bell-labs like culture in how the Department evaluates and awards proposals. With colleagues from LBNL, he developed an improved methodology for setting federal appliances standards. Chu was personally tasked by President Obama to assist BP in stopping the Deepwater Horizon oil leak in the Gulf of Mexico and to assist the Government of Japan with the tsunami-damaged nuclear reactors at Fukushima-Daiichi.
After his government service, Chu has returned to Stanford to become Professor of Physics and Professor of Molecular and Cellular Physiology, where he will teach and continue his research in biophysics, biomedicine, energy and energy economics.
The holder of 10 patents, Dr. Chu has published ~250 scientific and technical papers. In addition to the Nobel Prize and numerous other honors, he is a member of the National Academy of Sciences, the American Philosophical Society, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the Academia Sinica, and a foreign member of the Royal Academy of Engineering, the Chinese Academy of Sciences, and the Korean Academy of Sciences and Technology, Honorary Fellow of the Institute of Physics and Honorary Member of the Optical Society of America.
He earned an A.B. degree in mathematics, and a B.S. degree in physics from the University of Rochester, a Ph.D. in physics from the University of California, Berkeley, and has been awarded 23 honorary degrees.
From Dept. of Physics website: href="https://physics.stanford.edu/people/faculty/steven-chu" show="new" title="Dept. of Physics website" >https://physics.stanford.edu/people/faculty/steven-chu
Description of the Collection
Papers pertain primarily to topics in physics and include notes, overhead transparencies from his lectures, reprints, articles, memos, grants, correspondence, charts, and drawings. Subjects include electric dipole moment, diode lasers, and dye lasers; and there are some materials pertaining to departmental matters.
Lasers.; Physics -- Study and teaching.; Stanford University. Department of Physics; Chu, Steven.; Chu, Steven.
- Papers
  - Dipole Cooling and Electron Measurement (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Electron Measurement & Comparison of Electron & Positron g Factors (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fret Chirp for Slowing Atoms (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Harvey Gould – Electric Dipole Moment Experiments (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - EDM Calculations (includes "Micro-gravity Atomic Clocks and an Improved Search of the Cesium Electric Dipole Moment" – proposal to NASA March 1995) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Atomic Beams Blueprints (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bell Set-Up Material (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence from John Sapirstein and Allen Mills, 1989-90 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Muonium charts, articles, notes, correspondence, 1977-87 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Congratulations and other Messages, 1985, 1997-2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Picosec Photo Ionization (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Positronium (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Polarized E – sources (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Circular States & PS Dropping (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bell Labs PS Expt. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - PS/Titanium Sapphire (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - PS 15-25 Calculations for Data Analysis (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Stanford Linear Collider (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Controlling the Monster – Stanford and the Growth of Physics Research, 1935-1962 by P. Galison, B. Hevly, and R. Lowen, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Wolf Prize (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fund Raising, Bio-X, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Robert Irwin, Disc – correspondence, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Motee Scrapbook (1/2) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Motee Scrapbook (2/2) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 5th Force (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Faculty Salaries/Retirement (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - VUV (122mm) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Water (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Assorted Physics News/Updates (U. of Chicago, U of Toronto, etc) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Stanford Football, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Publications Involving Chu (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Other Miscellaneous Documents – Correspondence, Newsletters, Booklets, etc. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Syncros & Resolution (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Smithsonian, letters from Paul Forman, physics curator, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - NIH Advisory Material (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook (1/2) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook (2/2) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bell Labs, correspondence, 1987-91 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re various talks, post-Nobel prize (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Crack Pot Theories (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Applied Physics Advisees (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Visiting Committee (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Physics Dept. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Blueprints (A. Cable) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Laser Blueprints (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - TL Cell Blueprints (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Bistable Fabry-Perot Resonator (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Varian Lab Renovation (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mike Browne Blueprints (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Berry’s Phase: articles about (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Bates/Damgaard, article 1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Bob Byer, articles by (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - B Ba B2 O4 [B-Barium Borate] (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Cavity QED (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - B. Cabrera, articles by (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Charge Neutrality, articles about (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Chupp, T.E., article, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Collision Broadening of Spectral Lines (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Casimir Forces (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Coherent Population Trapping (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Coherent Optical Spectroscopy (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Charmonium (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Diode Laser (1/2) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Diode Lasers (2/2) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - High Power Diode Lasers (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Diamond Pinholes (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Laser Diodes for Spectroscopy (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Dinosaur Extinction (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Dysprosium (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Tuning Dye Lasers (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Absorption Spectra for Various Dyes, Mostly Coumarins (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Dye Laser Amplifiers (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Danzmann, Karsten – articles by (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - DNA (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photobleaching of Dyes (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - DYE Lasers ed F.P Schafer (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - C.W. Dye Laser Designs (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Dye Laser Designs (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Dye Laser Survey Papers – Snavely (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Transparencies 1 [lecture notes] (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Transparencies 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Transparencies 3 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Transparencies 4 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Transparencies 5 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Transparencies 6 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Transparencies 7 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Transparencies 8 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Transparencies 9 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Transparencies 10 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Transparencies 11 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Transparencies 12 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Transparencies 13 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Transparencies 14 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Transparencies 15 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Transparencies 16 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Additional papers, Accession ARCH-2013-061
  - Publications
    - American Scientist Interview, 1988 Jan (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Scanning Electromagnetic Transmission Line Microscope with Sub-Wavelength Resolution, 1989 Jan 01 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Precision Measurements of the 1S-2S Interal in Positronium, 1986 Jun 06 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Normal-incidence reflection of slow atoms from an optical evanescent wave, 1990 Mar 03 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notes and Letters for MS A83001, 1983 Feb 02 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Theoretical Analysis of Velocity-Selective Raman Transitions, 1991 Oct 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Observation of the 62p1/2-72P1/2 M1 Transtion in Atomic Thallium Vapor, 1977 Feb 07 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Laser-Cooled Cs Frequency Standard and a Measurement of the Frequency Shift due to Ultracold Collisions, 1993 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Observation of the Forbidden Magnetic Dipole Transition 62p1/2->17P1/2 in Atomic Thallium, 1976 Oct (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Initiation and re-initiation of DNA unwiding by the Escherichia coli Rep helicase, 2002 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Obersvation and Manipulation of Single DNA Molecules using Optical Tweezers and Fluorescecnce Microscopy (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The manipulation of neutral particles, 1998 Jul (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Biology and Polymer physics at the single-molecule level, 2003 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Precision Atom Interferometry with Light Pulses, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - An Atomic Interferometer Based on Adiabatic Population Transfer, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Single-Polymer Dynamics in Steady Shear Flow, 1999 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cold-collision properties derived from frequencey shifts in a cesium fountain, 1993 Nov (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Measurement of the positronium 13S1-23S1 interval by continuous-wave two-photon excitiation, 1993 Jul (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Precision Measurements with Cold Atoms (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Modern Physics: Serway, 1996 Mar (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Laser Cooling of Atoms, Ions, or Molecules by Coherent Scattering, 1999 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Precision Atom Terferometry and an Improved Measurement of the 13S1-23S2 Transition in Positronium, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Atom (for McGraw-Hill Yearbook of Science and Technology), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Applications of Laser Cooling and Trapping, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Measurement of an electron's electric dipole moment using Ccs atoms trapped in optical lattices, 2001 Feb 06 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Observation of Polymer Conformation Hysteresis in Extensional Flow, 2003 Sep 12 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Brownian dynamics simulations of a DNA moelcule in an extensional flow field, 1998 Dec 11 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Visualisation of Molecular Fluctuations near the Critical Point of the Coil-Stretch Transition in Polymer Elongation, 2003 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Dynamics of dilute and semidilute DNA solutions in the start-up of shear flow, 2000 Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Laser Cooling Below a Photon Recoil with Three Level Atoms, 1992 Jun 16 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Future Slow-atom Frequency Standards, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Atomic Terferometer Based on Adiabatic Population Transfer, 1994 June 02 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - A Random Walk in Science, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - A Single Molecule Study of the Elastic Properties of DNA, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence on "The normal mode structure of extended single molecules of DNA", 1996 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Thermodynamics of postronium thermal desorption from surfaces, 1981 Mar 01 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - The dynamics of partially extended single molecules of DNA, 1997 Jul 10 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Single-ion-pair fluorescence rations in ruby and Anderson localization, 1981 Jun 8 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Single Polymers in an Elongational Flow, 1997 May 08 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Response of Flexible Polymers to a Sudden Elongational Flow, 1998 Aug 28 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Single-Polymer Dynamics in Steady Shear Flow, 1999 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Hydrodanimics of a DNA Molecule in a flow field, 1996 Aug 19 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Precision measurement of h/mCs based on photon recoil using laser-cooled atoms and atomic interferometry, 1994 May 06 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Measurement of the Postronium 13S1-23S1 Interval by Continuous-Wave Two-Photon Excitation, 1993 Mar 08 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Improved magneto-optic trapping in a vapor cell, 1991 Dec 03 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Interview in American Scientist, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Cooling and Trapping of Atoms with Laser Light, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Atomic Spin Polarization by Raman cooling, 1997 Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Linear Pulse Propogation in an Absorbing Medium, 1981 Nov 30 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Various Papers on the Laser Cooling of Atoms, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - High-brightness atom sources for atomic fountains, 2001 Apr 9 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Dynamics of dilute and semidilute DNA solutions in the start-up of shear flow, 2000 Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - The Microscopic and Macroscopic Response of a Polymeric Fluid to the Start-Up of Shear Flow, 1999 Dec 15 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - A Proposal to NASA for the Study Of: Micro-gravity Atomic Clocks and an Improved Search of the Cesium Electric Dipole Moment, 1995 Mar (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Atom (for the McGraw-Hill yearbook of Science and Technology), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Future Slow-atom Frequency Standards, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Singer Polymer Dynamics in a Elongational Flow, 1997 Jun 27 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Dynamical Scaling of DNA Diffusion Coefficients, 1995 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Laser-Cooled Cs Frequency Standard and a Measurement of the Frequency Shift due to Ultracold Collisions, 1993 Jan 11 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Evaporative Cooling in a Crossed Dipole Trap, 1994 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Raman Cooling of Atoms in an Optical Dipole Trap, 1995 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Preliminary Observation of Parity Nonvonservation in Atomic Thallium, 1978 Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Observation of Low-Field Feshbach Resonances in Collisions of Cesium Atoms, 1998 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - "Particle Traps" Encyclopedia Article, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Single Molecule Observation of Liposome-Bilayer Fusion Thermally Induced by Soluble N-Ethyl Maleimide Sensitive-Factor Attachment Proteien Receptors (SNAREs), 2004 Aut 26 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Relating the Microscopic and Macroscopic Response of a Poluymeric Fluid in a Shearing Flow, 2000 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Correlating Structural Dynamics and Function in Single Ribozyme Molecules., 2002 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Fluorescence quenching: A tool for single-molecule protien-folding study, 2000 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Progress towards a Measurement of h/Mcs, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Measurement of the positronium 1 3S1-2 3S2 interval by continuous-wave two-photon excitation, 1993 Jul (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Stretching of a Single Tethered Polymer in a Uniform Flow, 1995 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Atomic Interferometry Using Stimulated Raman Transitions, 1991 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Measurement of the Gravitational Acceleration of an Atom with a Light-Pulse Atom Interferometer, 1992 Jan 10 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Precision atom interferometry, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Self-Diffusion of an Entangled DNA Molecule by Reptation, 1995 Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Cold atoms and quantum control, 2002 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Bimodal Velocity Distributions in Laser Cooled Atoms, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Fluorescence Signal vs Time of Flight Graphs, Undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Atom Funnel for the Production of a Slow, High-Density Atomic Beam, 1990 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Measurement of gravitational acceleration by dropping atoms, 1999 Aug 26 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Steve Chu Autobiographical Sketch, 1998 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - A Single-Molecule Study of RNA catalysis and Folding, 2000 Jun 16 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Following conformational changes of single bio-molecules in real time, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - The impact of Asian immigration on US Physics, Undated (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Single-Molecule Hydrodynamics of Tethered and Released DNA Molecules, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Beyond Optical Molasses: 3D Raman Sideband Cooling of Atomic Cesium to High Phase-Space Density, 2000 Jan 17 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Laser cooling: Beyond optical molasses and beyond closed transitions, Undated (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Ligand-induced conformational changes observed in single RNA molecules, 1999 Aug (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Suppression of Atomic Radiative Collisions by Tuning the Ground State Scattering Length, 1999 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Arthur Schawlow Obituary, 1999 Aug (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Review of How the Laser Happened: Adventures of a Scientist, 1999 Apr (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Laser Cooling due to Atomic Dipole Orientation, 1988 Sep 22 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - New Surprises in Laser Cooling, Undated (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Laser Spectroscopy of Positronium and Muonium, 1988 Jul (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Laser Cooling and Manipulation of Atoms, and Selected Applications., Undated (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - Laser Manipulation of Atoms and Particles, 1991 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Raman Cooling of Atoms in 2 and 3 Dimensions, 1993 Nov 29 (Box 1, Folder 97)